<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Truth vindicating itself from treason and rebellion, or, A brief discovery how the faith of the Grace of God to manward, in, and through Christ Jesus our Lord, who once appeared in the end of the world, to put away sin by the sacrifice of himself, and by means thereof is Saviour of the world as likewise the hope of his appearing the second time without sin, to the salvation of them that look for him : not onely clears itself from, but most directly and severely reproves all manner of sedition, and resisting the powers that God by his providence sets over us, whether they be good and gentle to us, or whether they be froward, and rise up against us / by Th. Moore Junior.</title>
            <author>Moore, Thomas, Junior.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B43467</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">625106328</idno>
  <idno type="VID">211280</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240886321</idno>
  
            <idno type="OCLC"> 625106328</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocn 625106328</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2608</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B43467)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 211280)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2968:35)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Truth vindicating itself from treason and rebellion, or, A brief discovery how the faith of the Grace of God to manward, in, and through Christ Jesus our Lord, who once appeared in the end of the world, to put away sin by the sacrifice of himself, and by means thereof is Saviour of the world as likewise the hope of his appearing the second time without sin, to the salvation of them that look for him : not onely clears itself from, but most directly and severely reproves all manner of sedition, and resisting the powers that God by his providence sets over us, whether they be good and gentle to us, or whether they be froward, and rise up against us / by Th. Moore Junior.</title>
                  <author>Moore, Thomas, Junior.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes "An instruction occasioned by the pride and insurrection of evil men, under pretence of godlinesse; as it was propounded to the consideration of others in writing, Jan. 16, 1660. Now published for more general usefulness, by Th. Moore Junior" on p. 21-35.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, tightly bound and with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Providence and government of God --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Kingdom of God --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Grace (Theology) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:211280:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:211280:2"/>
            <p>TRUTH Vindicating it self from TREASON AND REBELLION. OR, A brief discovery how the Faith of the Grace of God to manward, in, and through Christ Jesus our Lord, who once appeared in the end of the world, to put away sin by the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of himself, and by means thereof is the Saviour of the world; As likewise the hope of his appearing the second time without sin, to the salvation of them that look for him; not onely clears it self from, but most directly and severely reproves all manner of Sedition, and resisting the powers that God by his providence sets over us, whether they be good and gentle to us, or whether they be froward, and rise up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst us.</p>
            <p>By TH: MOORE Junior.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author. 1661.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:211280:3"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:211280:3"/>
            <head>TRUTH Vindicating it self from TREASON &amp; REBELLION.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Truth believed and professed by us concerning Christ,</p>
            <p n="1">1. In what he hath already done in, and by himself, as the Son of God, and Saviour of the world.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In what he is now become, and doing for us in the name of the Father, as the Saviour of all men, especially of them that believe: And</p>
            <p n="3">3. In what he will do to the utmost salvation of them that believe, and wait for him.</p>
            <p>These being the great things of Gods Law, as they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive not testimony from man, or depend not on that for their authority, so neither need they any mans help to vindicate them from any lye, or unreasonable and unjust thing toward God, or man, but doe fully acquit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves by their direct and cleare opposition to every cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt principle and practice. We shall therefore say no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to vindicate them, or the sincete professors of them, from those evil thoughts and speeches that may be occasioned by the wicked, and ungodly practises of some such, as having a <hi>form of godliness, deny the power thereof;</hi> but onely assert them briefly under some few heads of them, and shew what they are, and what instructions do
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:211280:4"/>naturally arise from them, as we have received them from the testimony of the Lord, and let them speak for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves.</p>
            <p>That when <hi>all had sinned,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/>
               <hi>and come short of the glory of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom 3.23, 24. with ch. 5.6-12-18. Joh. 3.16. &amp; 4.42. 1 Joh. 4.14 Joh. 3.17. Gal. 1.4. &amp; 4.4.</note> in and unto which they were created in the first <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam;</hi> yea, when they were become altogether filthy, and enemies to God; yet <hi>God so loved the world</hi> of mankinde, <hi>that he gave his onely begotten Son</hi> the Saviour thereof, <hi>that whosoever</hi> of them (through his grace in, and through this unspeakable gift of Grace, bringing Salvation to all men in due time) <hi>believeth in him, should not perish, but have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlasting life. For God sent not his Son into the world to condemn the world, but that the world through him might be saved.</hi> And that this onely begotten Son of God, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the will of God the Father, by whom he was fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordained and appointed to this work from the beginning, and with whom his undertaking was accepted, &amp; precious to this end;
<note place="margin">Heb. 9.26. 1 Tim. 1.15. Luke 19.10. Heb. 2.9. 1 Pet. 3.18. 1 Tim. 2.4.6.</note> He <hi>in the fulness of time, once in the end of the world,</hi> came into the world, and appeared in a body, won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully <hi>prepared</hi> for him, in the womb of a Virgin was <hi>made of a woman, made under the Law, to redeem them that were under the law;</hi> to save sinners, even that which was lost; <hi>And he by the grace of God tasted death for every man, the just for the unjust;</hi> He <hi>gave himself a ransome for all;</hi> and by the meanes thereof is <hi>the mediator between God and men,</hi> that he might be testified, or himself be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a testimony in due time; that so he might <hi>bring us to God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. This principle evinceth, that all were lost by sin, even become <hi>dead in sins and trespasses,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Corin. 5.14, 15, 16.</note> and <hi>by nature children of wrath,</hi> one as well as another. <hi>Forasmuch</hi> (saith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle) <hi>as one died for all; we therefore,</hi> and from thence <hi>judge that all were dead;</hi> and therefore henceforth, since we have received this judgement, we judge, or <hi>know no man after the flesh,</hi> or <hi>as the wisdome of the flesh teacheth,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to outward or fleshly differences;
<note place="margin">Rom 3.23.</note> for <hi>there is no difference, for all have sinned, and come short of the glory of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:211280:4"/>
            <p>By this Doctrine all are proved to be under sin in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, and as from <hi>Adam;</hi> whence it is affirmed of them that now believe,
<note place="margin">Eph. 2.3.</note>
               <hi>That they were by nature the children of wrath, even as others;</hi> and <hi>sometimes foolish, disobedient,</hi> &amp;c. walking with others after the course of this world. And this is one, (and a principall one) of those Instructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<note place="margin">Rom. 3.9-19.23-27.</note> by which the doctrine of Faith <hi>excludes boasting</hi> eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where, or in any thing, but onely in the Lord, where others may rejoyce with us; for this shews there was no difference, either as in our selves, or as in respect of our state and condition before God, as in and from fallen <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam.</hi> Therefore if we have received any thing that makes us differ,
<note place="margin">☜</note> it is of free grace, even of that love and pity that is in him to manward:
<note place="margin">Eph. 2.3, 4, 5.</note> nor was there any thing that did make God a debtor to us, or more intitle us to such mercy then others, but even for that love wherewith he loved us, when dead in sins and trespasses, and wherewith he still loveth others, that are still such as we sometimes were; he hath shewed mercy on us, that in us he might shew a pattern of the exceeding riches of his kindness to others, such as we. <hi>For we were as sheep going astray,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.25. with ver. 18-21. &amp;c.</note>
               <hi>but are now returned to the chief Bishop and shepherd of our souls.</hi>—</p>
            <p>This the Apostle <hi>Peter</hi> useth as a principall motive, to engage believing servants and subjects to be subject to their own Masters and Rulers after the flesh, (those by Gods providence set over them,
<note place="margin">Tit. 3.1, 2, 3, 4. Rom. 3. Pro. 13.10. with Jam. 3. <hi>totum.</hi> 1 Cor. 6.11 with Tit. 3.4. &amp;c. 1 Pet. 3.21, 22.</note> whether gentle or fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.) The Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> also with the like motive, <hi>puts them in minde to be subject to principalities and powers, to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey Magistrates. To speak evil of no man, to be no brawlers, but gentle, shewing all meekness to all men; for we our selves were sometimes foolish,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>For this being heartily minded, tends to hide pride from us, which is the onely root of contention, and so of confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, and every evil work. We were as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nclean as others in our selves, and in the sight of God; and it is by the Baptisme, or washing of regeneration in the name of the Lord Jesus, and by the Spirit of our God, in that foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:211280:5"/>opened for others, that we are in any measure sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This principle also with the former instruction in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formes,
<note place="margin">Tit. 2.11. with <hi>ch.</hi> 3.3, 4. 2 Cor. 5.15</note> and on all occasions minds us of that infinite love of pity, and compassion in God to manward, even to the dying sinner, while his sin is not finished; to the foolish, disobedient, rebellious and froward enemies, who are in no worse condition then we sometimes were;
<note place="margin">☞</note> for even when we were ungodly, enemies, under the sentence of death,
<note place="margin">Ps. 68.18-20. Rom. 5.6. Ezek. 33.10, 11. 1 Tim. 2.4.6. 2 Pet. 3.15 Jer. 17.16.</note> and ready to perish, <hi>in due time Christ died for the ungodly,</hi> evidencing clearly that Almighty God hath no pleasure at all in the death of the wicked that dieth; he would not that any should perish, but that through Christ they might come to repentance, and be saved. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore also he is kind to the unkind and evil, and exerciseth patience, forbearance, &amp; bounty towards them, which we ought to account to be salvation. The which being dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently heard &amp; believingly minded by us, would frame us to some like-mindedness with him; that we should not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sten the wofull day to any,
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.43, 44, &amp;c. Luke 6.27. &amp;c. Ch. 9.53.55, 56.</note> but <hi>love our enemies, bless them that curse us, pray for them that despightfully use us and persecute us.</hi> Therefore, saith our Saviour, <hi>I say unto you</hi> that hear, <hi>Love your enemies,</hi> &amp;c. And with this instruction he reproves his Disciples desire of fire to come down from Heaven, to consume such as would not receive him; <hi>Ye know not</hi> (saith he) <hi>of what spirit you are; for the Son of man came not to destroy mens lives, but to save them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. This principle likewise minds us of the way, or means by which he first testified his love to us sinners, and through which his love is still commended, and the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness of God declared in shewing mercy to us, to be nothing less then the wonderful abasement and sufferings of Jesus Christ in the flesh for our sins,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.18 &amp; 4 1.</note>
               <hi>The just for the unjust, that he might bring us to God;</hi> which not onely shewes the altogether lostness and filthiness of man, see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he could have help and mercy no other way; and the infinite greatness and strength of his love that could not be quenched by so many waters as all our sorrows, but for
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:211280:5"/>the joy set before him endured, even for that love and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty he had to manward, when dead in sins and trespasses, as beforesaid: But this likewise directs us the way which he hath himself trodden and consecrated for us to walk in, in our seeking the good of others that are yet froward,
<note place="margin">Rom. 15.1, 2. 1 Cor. 10.33. Mat 20 28 Mat. 5.39. &amp;c. Rom 12.18. &amp;c.</note> and enemies; as also in which our selves may be sanctified and prepared for that glory to be revealed, <hi>viz.</hi> to become servants to all, so as for their good to edification, even as <hi>the Son of man came not to be ministred unto, but to minister, and to give his life a ransome for many:</hi> not to seek glory of men, or great things for our selves among them, nor to strive with them, to resist the evil they render to us for his names sake, but to seek to overcome their evil with good, and in a patient enduring their reproaches, revilings, and evil intreaties, yea laying down our lives for Christs sake, that he may be glorified; and for the brethren, that the truth of the Gospel may continue with them, and so a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst and for the good of others. In this way we have the promise of his gracious and powerfull Presence with us, to strengthen, protect, and deliver from the evil, and make us partakers of the fruit of his righteousness; and who are they (to be compared with him) that would harm us, if we be followers of that which is good?
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.9-13.14. Rom. 8.17</note>
               <hi>But if we suffer for righteousness sake, happy are we; the spirit of glory and of God resteth upon us,</hi> &amp;c. Yea, <hi>if we suffer with him, we shall reign with him,</hi> and be glorified together.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Forasmuch then as Christ hath suffered for us in the flesh, arm your selves with the same minde,</hi> to be doers and suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferers of the will of God from the heart, and therein, and according thereto, to be servants to all, and sufferers here in the flesh, waiting for that Kingdom and Glory to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed: For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. He suffered, the just for the unjust, yet <hi>when reviled, reviled not again; when he suffered he threatned not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.21, 22, 23. 1 Pet. 2.24, 25. ch. 3.18.</note>
               <hi>leaving us an example, that we should follow his steps.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. In his sufferings <hi>he bare our sins in his own body on the tree,</hi> that <hi>we being dead to sin,</hi> redeemed from the curse of the Law, <hi>should live unto righteousness,</hi> and <hi>by his stripes
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:211280:6"/>we are healed;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 1.20.24. Heb. 1.3.</note> peace and atonement is made, <hi>He hath by himself purged away our sins</hi> that were imputed to him from before the Father, <hi>and is set down on the right hand of God,</hi> so that the wrath of God, the curse of the Law, that is the due and proper wages of our sins, is not left in our sufferings, but the savour of his oyntments (who hath turned them from Curses into Blessings, even into sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied instruments of preparing us for Glory) is left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him in them, that we may comfortably pass after him.</p>
            <p>The second Head we shall here mention of the foresaid principles, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> is this, That by means of the abasement and sufferings of Christ in the flesh, and his giving himself a ransome for all;
<note place="margin">Phil. 2.7-12. Act. 10.36. Rom. 14.9. 2 Sam. 14.14. Heb. 2.14, 15.</note> He, even the man Christ Jesus, is <hi>Lord of all, to the glory of God the Father,</hi> whose Kingdome is thereby brought unto us, and ruleth over all; so as that whereas we were justly banished from God in the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous sentence of his Law, and in the equity of his Justice, and could have had no gracious Kingdome, or protection of God over us; but being banished from God, must ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarily have remained in our sin and death under the bondage of Satan all our life-time; ye a we must have been left to all generations in our confusion and disorder that sin had brought upon us, as the fishes of the Sea, and as the creeping things, that have no ruler over them, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so shut out for ever from any hope: This being our condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by reason of sin entring into the world; Jesus Christ, who verily was fore-ordained, and by vertue of his undertaking accepted with the Father, as the Lord, and Christ, even before the foundation or beginning of the world,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.20. Col. 1.14-17 with Ps. 75.3. Heb. 9.26. with ch. 2.14, 15. Joh. 12.31 32. Gal. 3.13.</note> as now it stands (for <hi>by him,</hi> as so considered, <hi>all things consist,</hi> since by sin they were dissolved:) He having <hi>once in the end of the world appeared</hi> in a body prepared for him in mans nature, subject to all our infirmities; but <hi>without sin,</hi> that he might put away our sin by the sacrifice of himself; and having in that body born and suffered the judgement of this world, having been made sin and a curse for us: He now in his Resurrection and Ascension in the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:211280:6"/>same body in which he bore our sins on the tree, hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually obtained of the Father,
<note place="margin">Mat. 11.27 &amp; 28.18.</note> and gloriously received in the man, a release of mankind from under that sentence of banishment, the curse of the Law unto himself, who hath bought them, so that the Father hath delivered all men and all things into his hands, as,
<note place="margin">Joh. 5.22-27.</note> and <hi>because he is the Son of man,</hi> and given him <hi>all power in heaven and earth,</hi> as the Lord and Saviour of the world of mankind: For <hi>the Father judgeth no man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 14.7.9.</note>
               <hi>but hath committed all judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Son, and hath given him authority to execute judgement also, because he is the Son of man:</hi> For <hi>to this end Christ both died and rose, and revived</hi> (or lived again) in that body in which he bore our sins, <hi>that he might be Lord of all: whether therefore we live or die, we are the Lords,</hi> at his dispose, and under his government,
<note place="margin">Col. 1.14,15. 1 Joh. 5.11, 12. Ro. 8.32. Act. 5.31.</note>
               <hi>who gave himself a ransome for us:</hi> and in him eternall redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and life is prepared for us, by means of his death, and so given us in him, that with him it might be given to us. <hi>Him hath God exalted a Prince and a Saviour, for to give unto sinfull men,</hi> yea to rebellious sinners, such as <hi>Israel</hi> that crucified him, <hi>repentance and forgiveness of sins.</hi> And to this purpose God hath <hi>glorified the man Christ Jesus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 17.4, 5. with ch. 1.1-14. Heb. 4.14. ct 9.24. 1 Tim. 2.5, 6. Isa. 53.12. Eph. 1.21, 22. Heb 2.8. 1 Pet. 3.22 Ps. 68.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8. &amp;c.</note>
               <hi>with his own self, with the glory he had with the Father</hi> (as the eternall and onely begotten Son of God) <hi>before the world was,</hi> that now in that glory he may <hi>appear in the presence of God for us,</hi> the onely and powerfull Mediator between God and men, and to make intercession for the transgres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors; and that in the same name and glory of the Father he may also execute the judgement and government of God over us, as the King of kings and Lord of lords, who being <hi>ascended on high, far above all principalities and powers,</hi> and having <hi>a name given him that is above every man that is named, not onely in this world, but in that to come,</hi> hath therein <hi>received gifts for men, yea for the rebellious also that the Lord God might dwell among them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. This Principle instructs us, That <hi>by him Kings reign,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 8.15, 16.</note>
               <hi>and Princes decree justice; by him Princes rule, and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, even all the Judges of the earth;</hi> that all Thrones,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:211280:7"/>Principalities and Powers are created by him, and for him,
<note place="margin">Col. 1.15-18. Rev. 1.5. Psal. 75.7.</note> and <hi>by him all things consist,</hi> even as he is <hi>the first be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten from the dead;</hi> that he is <hi>the Prince of the Kings of the earth;</hi> and that it is he that pulls down and sets up at his pleasure, even now in this time while he sees it good to give the Kingdomes of this world into the hand of the children of men; yet himself sits in the stern, and gives and takes away, orders and disposes at his pleasure.</p>
            <p>And this engageth the hearty believer of this truth, to yield honour and subjection to such Masters or Rulers, in, or after the flesh,
<note place="margin">Eph. 6.5-8 Col. 3.22-1 1 Sam. 8.3.7. Ch. 10.24.27.</note> as by his providence are over us; and that for his sake, that in reverence to his infinite wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, power and faithfulness in ordering all things: for indeed, in not so yielding subjection to them, as in the Lord, and for the Lords sake, they being set up and made to stand by him; there is a secret calling his wisdome and faithfulness into question, and so a rejecting or resisting, not of them onely, but of him from being our King, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour and Disposer. And so much the Apostle argues and concludes from the premises,
<note place="margin">Ro. 13.1, 2, 3. with Col. 1.16, 17.</note>
               <hi>(viz.)</hi> That <hi>the powers that be are ordained,</hi> or ordered, made, and made to stand, set up, and pulled down, <hi>by God;</hi> and that is so as by Christ, by whom be judgeth and executeth judgement. <hi>Whosoever therefore</hi> (saith he) <hi>resisteth the power, resisteth the ordinance of God; and they that resist shall receive to themselves damnation,</hi> as a resister of God in one of his great and gracious ordinances, for the preservation of mens lives, and keeping them in good order, that they might seek the Lord;
<note place="margin">Col. 3.24, 25. Eph. 6.8. Ro. 12.19. with Deut. 32.35, 36.</note> for to that end they are ordained by him; and whether they be faithfull to him in the trust committed to them, or no, to him they must give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, who is their great Master in Heaven, their Lord and ours, by whose providence they were set there, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for mercy, or as a chastisement to them over whom they are set; and vengeance belongs to him, not to us. And for our encouragement quietly to leave it to him, and willingly for his sake to be subject to principalities and powers, those at any time by his providence set over us, this principle further teacheth us,</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:211280:7"/>
            <p n="2">2. That he being so exalted (as aforesaid) still sitteth on the right hand of power,
<note place="margin">Ps. 110.1, 2 Mat. 11.27, 29. Mat 28.18 Psal. 9.16. Joh. 5.27. Prov. 21.1.</note> till all his enemies be made his footstool; and so, that in the Name and Glory of the Father, he still, and alwayes retains all power in Heaven and in Earth, all power with the Father, and over all things in his own hand, even that power which he gives to Angels or men, to any principalities or powers: He doth not so give it into their hands, as to give it out of his own; But still he hath it, and all authority in the name of the Father, to use it in the execution of Judgement, as King of kings, and Lord of lords, and to restrain or turn about their use or abuse of it, as he pleaseth, and as may serve for his ends, whether for mercy or judgement; even the hearts and hands of Kings are in the hands of the Lord, and he turneth them about as the rivers of water which way soever he pleaseth: And so God,
<note place="margin">Psal. 47.7. &amp; 115.3. Psal. 11.4. 1 Sam. 2.2, 3. Ps. 144.10. with Ps. 82 Act. 17.24-27.</note> even the Father, is in, and by Jesus Christ, King of all the earth; he hath done in all overturnings, and still doth whatever he pleaseth in heaven and in earth, and in all places: The Lords throne is in heaven, whence his eyes behold, and his eye-lids try the children of men; and he is a God that weigheth actions; he giveth greatness and salvation un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Kings, and more abundant teaching, with instruction and admonition to use it well, as their place and trust is greater: And this for the love and good will he bears to mankind, that they may in their severall places and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations be preserved and kept in order, that they might <hi>seek him</hi> (the Lord) <hi>while he may be found.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ps. 82. &amp; 75.</note> And if at any time those set up over men by him, will not understand, or learn of him, (as is complained of the generality of them) but lift up the horn, or strength given them, contrary to his end, and counsel, to the countenance of evil doers, and shame and grief of the just: yet he that sitteth in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, knowes how to make their counsels and actions, in which they intend otherwise, serve his ends, even to cause the wrath of man to praise him in the issue of it, to tend (contrary to their meaning) <hi>to the praise of them that do well,</hi> by purifying them, and making them to shine
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:211280:8"/>forth more clear in their patient enduring for his sake, and to the shame,
<note place="margin">Prov. 16.4. Isa. 10.6, 7. Dau. 11.35</note> confusion and <hi>terrour of them that do evil,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in those things they do to countenance them, or strengthen their hands therein, or otherwise as he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feth: for he hath made, ordained, and ordered all things for himself, and to serve his own ends, even them that make themselves wicked, and fit themselves for such dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honourable uses, he hath ordained them for his rods, to scourge an hypocriticall nation, and for the purifying and making white his people to the time of the end, and knows how to use them and their wrath to serve his ends (though they mean not so) and then to restrain the remainder of their wrath;
<note place="margin">Ps. 76.12. &amp; 89.9. with 65.7. &amp; Ps. 93.</note> for he that <hi>ruleth the raging of the sea, and saith, Hitherto shall thy proud waves come, and no further;</hi> He also <hi>stilleth the tumult of his people,</hi> for the Lord most high is mightier then the noyse of many waters, yea then the mighty waves of the sea, even then when they lift up their voyce;
<note place="margin">Exo. 18.11 Ps. 73.28. Isa. 8.11, 12.</note>
               <hi>in the thing which they deal proudly, and lift up the horn, he is,</hi> and will be, <hi>above them;</hi> therefore <hi>holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness becomes his house for ever: It is good for us to draw near to God,</hi> to sanctifie him in our hearts, and make him our fear and our dread, to put our trust in him, that we may declare his wonderfull works, and <hi>walk before him in the land of the living;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ps. 62. Gen. 18.25</note> for <hi>all power belongs to him,</hi> and with him also is infinite wisdome, mercy and faithfulness, and so all fitness <hi>to render to every man according to his work: And shall not the Judge of all the earth do right?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence therefore we may learn, and be encouraged cheerfully to <hi>commit the keeping of our souls to him in well doing, as unto a faithfull Creator,</hi> by whom, and for whose pleasure all things, and so all principalities and powers are and were created:
<note place="margin">Ro. 13.3, 4.</note> and therefore, not to be afraid, or deterred from doing that which is good, though the spirit of any of our Rulers, or Masters, after the flesh, should rise up against us therein. For because he is the head of all principality and power, therefore if we do that which is good, we shall have praise even of the power that he sets over us; whether they observe and walk in his counsel,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:211280:8"/>or not, he will make them, and that which they do, in his time and way, and at least in the issue tend to our praise in well doing: But <hi>if we do evil, be afraid of the power,</hi> as it is his instrument, and in his hand; for though they should intend, and promise, and do that which may be for the countenancing and strengthening the hands of evil doers, yet forasmuch as they are his servants and instruments in his hand, to execute wrath on them that do evil, we may justly fear, they and their power shall be made a terrour to us, by him that sits in the stern, either more directly, or in the issue, though they intend not so.
<note place="margin">Eccles 5.8.</note>
               <hi>And if at any time we see the oppression of the poor, and violent perverting of judgement and justice in a Province, yet marvail not,</hi> nor be astonished <hi>at the matter,</hi> as if the ordinance of the Lord should not stand and take place in every age, place, and business; but be silent before the Lord that reigneth, as knowing that <hi>he who is higher then the highest regardeth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ps. 103.19, 20, 21, 22. 2 King. 6.16, 17. Heb. 1.14.</note> to give to every man in his way and time according to his work: And there is also in his hand, as his servants, other more glorious instruments, such as be <hi>higher then they,</hi> even the holy Angels, the innumerable multitude of the heavenly host, by which he oft turns about the inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our powers, and their consultations and actings as he pleaseth. <hi>Are not they all ministring spirits sent forth</hi> and imployed by the Captain of our salvation, and especially <hi>for the good of the heirs of salvation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. This principle also directs us how, or in what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to yeild subjection to principalities and powers, and to <hi>obey Magistrates</hi> in the Lord, and <hi>for the Lords sake,</hi> informing us what that fear, honour, and subjection is, that is due unto them by the order &amp; appointment of him that is exalted far above all principality and power, who is their Lord and ours: And that is such, as is contained in, and subordinate, and subservient to, and so stands together with that worshipping and serving onely, and making him our fear and our dread, unto which we are obliged by his great and gracious Lordship over us, by right of purchase:
<note place="margin">Ps. 45.10, 11.</note> for he is our Lord, and we must worship him. And in the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:211280:9"/>worshipping and serving him onely,
<note place="margin">Ro. 13.1-7. Rev. 19.2-4. Eph. 6.5-8 Col. 3.22-25. 1 Tim. 6.1, 2. Tit. 2.9, 10 with 1 Cor. 7, 23. &amp; Isa. 8.11, 12.</note> This is contained, or included, that we render that fear, honour, and subjection unto men, which he hath made due unto them from us, by that place in which he hath set any of them over us, and according to his appoyntment, and that we yield this sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, fear, or reverence for the Lords sake, doing what we do therein, in <hi>singleness of heart as unto Christ,</hi> and with fear and trembling before him, not as men-pleasers, nor as the servants of men, or as making them the ultimate or single objects of our fear, and of our dread, but <hi>as the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God,</hi> doing his will therein <hi>from the heart,</hi> knowing that from him every one shall receive his reward accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his works, for we serve the Lord Christ.</p>
            <p>Now then for understanding what that honour and subjection is, that God hath made due from us to them, whom he by his providence orders to be over us, as chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of men; It is needfull first to consider in what place he the Lord of lords and King of kings hath set those his Vicegerents (of whom he hath said they are Gods in their severall places) over us; and so what is by his gift and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment theirs, and under their power, and what is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served by him in his own hand and power, to be peculiarly under his government, in the spiritual administration of it, that so we may know how to <hi>render to Caesar the things that be Caesars, and to God the things that be Gods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For our help in this, it is considerable, That God hath made and appointed them the Fathers and Masters of our flesh,
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.9. Eph. 6.5. Col. 3.22.</note> or our Fathers, Masters and Rulers after the flesh; for so we find, that not onely our parents by naturall generation are so called, but also Masters and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours of families, are said to be unto those under their authority, their masters after, or according to the flesh; and in some equivalent sense the same may be said and understood of the King or chief Principality and Power, as supreme amongst men, and of Magistrates and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours under them;
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.13-18. &amp;c.</note> for therefore the instructions to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving servants to be <hi>subject to their own masters accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the flesh,</hi> &amp; to them and other believers that are sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:211280:9"/>to yield subjection to their superiour Governours,
<note place="margin">Tit. 2.9. &amp;c.</note> are sometime conjoyned, to signifie the subjection requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red is of a like nature;
<note place="margin">with ch. 3.1, 2. 1 Tim. 6.1. &amp;c.</note> &amp; otherwhile the instruction to ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants subjection to their own Masters is onely mentioned, as including the other therein; those superiour powers in their higher places and capacities, being also our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, Fathers, or Rulers, according to the flesh, and that likewise in subordination to God in Christ,
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.9.</note> whose we are in soul and body, for <hi>he hath bought us with a price;</hi> but himself distinctly and peculiarly is <hi>the father of spirits.</hi> Yea further, to this purpose, we find, that the King and Governours under him, though ordained,
<note place="margin">Rom. 13.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1 Pet. 2.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> set up and sent by God (and so may be called <hi>ordinances of God,</hi> yet) are also called <hi>ordinances of men;</hi> and that not onely because usually ordained and set up by, or according to the choice and agreement of the people, as men, or coming to their power or places of trust by a humane right and title; but also because they are ordained and set over men (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Gods order and appointment) in things pertaining to them, as children of men;
<note place="margin">Dan 4.25.31. Joh. 18.36 Mat. 12.28 &amp; 21.43. &amp; 22.2. &amp;c.</note> therefore also their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes are called <hi>The Kingdomes of men,</hi> and signified to be of this world, even so as to distinguish them from that gracious &amp; spiritual administration of Gods Government by Jesus Christ, through and according to the Gospel, called frequently <hi>The Kingdom of God,</hi> &amp; <hi>the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their Mastership, Rule and Dominion is (at least prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally and directly) over such things as pertain onely to the outward man, and to this present life and world;
<note place="margin">1 Sa. 2.25. Hab. 1.14.</note> and this mastership, rule and dominion is given them, that in the use and exercise of it, they may preserve mens lives, and keep them in good order, from biting, devouring, or harming one another; and this to a higher end, that men might seek the Lord, and that to that purpose those that do seek him might <hi>under their protection lead a quiet and peaceable life, in all godliness and honesty.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 17.24.27 1 Tim. 2.1, 2.</note> And to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate them as instruments in the hands of God, to use their power effectually to such an end (by being <hi>a terrour to evil works, and for the praise of them that do well</hi>)
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:211280:10"/>power is given them over the flesh or body, in subordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to him,
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.10 Luk. 12.4.</note> such as by which they can and may, with Gods permission, correct us after their own pleasure, without asking leave of those under their authority: yea, the su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Governours under the said permission, may kill the body; and so much power is needfull to be given into their hands, to keep them under their authority, from killing or hurting one another, yet is not this power given out of his hand into theirs; he still hath <hi>all power in heaven and in earth,</hi> and so keeps the sole check and controll over them in that power he gives to them, and to him they are accountable for their use of it. But still he reserves in his own hand the fatherhood of, and after the Spirit, as his pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peculiar seat, and that is not onely to sit as Lord in the mind and conscience, but in order thereto, and that it may be by him (in the spirituall administration of his govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment through, and according to the Gospel) renewed, san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, regulated and preserved blameless unto the day of Christ, when the soul and body of them that worship and wait for him, shall be re-united in eternall life, in and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his glorious Kingdome:
<note place="margin">Mat. 23.8, 10. Isa. 33.22.</note> I say, in order thereto, to appoint and determine the matters pertaining to the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and to life everlasting; he is himself the onely ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster of our faith, fear, and worship towards God, and we are brethren, and so he onely is our Judge, our Law-giver, and our King; and he onely (and not the beast or world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly powers and principalities, though they have <hi>names of blasphemy</hi> attributed to any of them, or their Image) is so to be acknowledged and worshipped by us.</p>
            <p>Now then that we may <hi>give to Caesar that which is Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sars,</hi> and not that which peculiarly appertains to God in Christ,</p>
            <p>The flesh, or outward man, is to be yielded up in subjection, so as in the Lord, and for the Lords sake, as to say,</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is to be yielded up in obedience to their power, lawes and commands, in doing that which they require of us, though grievous to be born; if it be onely an oppressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:211280:10"/>on or grievance to the flesh, or outward man, or crosse to our will or appetite; if it may be done with a <hi>conscience voyd of offence towards God and man,</hi> and stand with the acknowledgement of the Lord, as the onely master of our faith, fear and worship, <hi>the father of our spirits.</hi> And in those good works they require, we are to be more ready then others, yea, the more ready and cheerfull in doing them, because required: And</p>
            <p n="2">2. If the things they require be such, as cannot be done by us without bringing our mind or spirit in bondage to the power of man in things pertaining to the Spirit,
<note place="margin">Tit. 3.1. with 1 Pet. 2.13. Col. 3.22.</note> and peculiar Kingdome of God; if they be such, as in doing which we cannot keep a good conscience towards God and man, or will not stand with the acknowledgement of the Lord, as the onely Father of our spirits: As to say, the having or owning any other Lord in his place or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, as the master of our faith, fear and worship; the making to our selves any image, or representation of him, or bowing to or worshipping any such as are made by men for and to us; the profaning his Name or Sabbath, the dishonouring or neglect of Parents, though under re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious pretences (as the Pharisees taught) the defraud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, wronging, or false accusing our neighbour,
<note place="margin">Mat. 15.4, 5, 6.</note> or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding good from the owner, as in not holding fast the profession of our faith in word and conversation, as we are taught of God, <hi>or forsaking the assembling of our selves together</hi> to that purpose; yet in such things as these, the flesh or outward man is also to be yielded up in subjection, but not in doing what they require;
<note place="margin">Mat. 22.21 Act. 4.19, 20. Rom. 6.13. Heb. 12.9, 10.</note> we must not give to <hi>Caesar</hi> the things that be Gods peculiar, nor yield such o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to men as in which the word of God is made voyd; our members are not to be yielded up as servants to unrighteousness, <hi>It is better to obey God then man;</hi> yet the flesh is to be yielded up in such cases, in a patient endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and suffering the punishment they inflict, when for conscience sake towards God we cannot do what they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn: though they correct us after their own will and pleasure, and wrongfully, we are to endure it patiently,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:211280:11"/>and still to give them that reverence, as still to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge them our masters by Gods appoyntment, according to the flesh; it is he that hath put it under their power, and for good ends, and we ought not to resist his ordinance, but yield them that is theirs, though they abuse their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,
<note place="margin">Exo 22.28 Act. 23.5. Mat. 5.39. &amp;c. 1 Pet. 3.9-14. with Isa. 8.11, 12, 13. Rom. 12.17-21. Isa. 28.16. 1 Pet. 2.6. Rom. 13. Pro. 24.21.</note> and not to threaten them when we suffer, <hi>not to curse the Gods, nor revile the rulers of the people,</hi> but still to <hi>bless and pray for our enemies and persecuters;</hi> And <hi>if we suffer for righteousness sake,</hi> and <hi>take it patiently, happy are we, the spirit of glory and of God resteth upon us;</hi> we are <hi>not to say a confederacy with any in their evil wayes,</hi> to save or defend our selves, either by having fellowship with any (though they have power on their side) in their unfruitfull works of darkness, but rather reprove them; or by complying with any (under what pretence soever) in resisting the powers that be, or the wrath and evil which they would wrongfully execute upon us, but rather give place to wrath, for vengeance is the Lords, and he shall repay: he that believes makes not haste, nor shall be confounded; but he that resisteth the power, resisteth the ordinance of God, and shall receive to himself damnation; therefore let us not meddle, nor have any thing to do with them that are given to change their God, or their King, for who knoweth the ruine of them both?</p>
            <p>Likewise this subjection of the outward man, or after the flesh,
<note place="margin">Eph. 6.5-8. Col. 3.22-25.</note> to our masters, fathers and rulers in and after the flesh, is so to be yielded by us, as in the Lord, in the faith, fear, and acknowledgement of him as the Lord of lords and King of kings, by whom these reign, and so as for his sake (as before is hinted) not doing what we doe, or yiel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding up the flesh to suffer what we are called to, as men-pleasers, or seeking praise therein of men, not out of strife and vain-glory, but as approving our hearts to God in singlenesse of heart, as unto Christ; neither making them our fear and our dread, but sanctifying the Lord of hosts in our hearts, and yielding our subjection to them in reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to him, and for conscience sake towards him, who is the principall object of our fear, and motive to our reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rencing
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:211280:11"/>them; and so in awfulnesse before him that hath put them in that place, and us in this, who is holy in all his wayes, and righteous in all his works. The fear of man bringeth a snare;
<note place="margin">Pro. 29.25, 26.</note> but whoso putteth his trust in the Lord shall be safe; many will seek the Rulers favour; but every mans judgement cometh from the Lord: The Lord reigneth, let all the inhabitants of the world fear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, and stand in aw of him.</p>
            <p>The last head we shall mention of the foresaid princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and but briefly propound, is this: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/>
            </p>
            <p>That the Son of man,
<note place="margin">Heb. 9.28. Mat. 16.27 &amp; 26.64. Act. 1.11. &amp; 3.19, 20. Rev. 1.7. 1 Thes. 4.14-16. 1 Joh. 3.1, 2.</note> even the Lord Jesus Christ him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self shall appear the second time, and that in the same bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in which he bore our sins on the tree, and is now recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved up into glory, and shall then come in the glory of his Father, which he now possesseth in heaven it self for us, and with his holy Angels; and then shall bring with him all that sleep in Jesus; for the Lord himself shall descend from heaven with a shout, with the voyce of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angel, and with the trump of God; and the dead in Christ shall rise first (namely, before the rest of the dead) and then the survivers of that body shall immediately be changed, and they together shall meet the Lord in the air, and so come and appear with him in glory, and be for ever with the Lord.</p>
            <p>Then, in that day of his second and glorious appearing,
<note place="margin">Col. 3.4. Rev. 11.15.17.18. Rom. 8.17, 18-23. Ps. 82.7, 8. with Psal. 2. <hi>tot.</hi> Dan. 7.18.22.27.</note> he shall take to him his great power, and reign; and those that now suffer with him, shall then in their raised and glorified bodies reign with him; then the Kingdomes of this world shall become the Kingdomes of the Lord; he shall then take the outward administration of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into his own hands, and give it to his Saints (the children of the first resurrection) and they shall admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster it with him; then the Saints (that are in this life and world, the filth and off-scouring of all things) shall judge the world.</p>
            <p>Then he shall create new heavens and new earth, in which righteousness shall dwell; for the heavens and the earth that are now, shall be dissolved and purged by
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:211280:12"/>fire;
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.2, 3. Luk. 19.12 &amp;c. 2 Pet. 3. 2 Tim. 4.1. 2 Cor. 5 10</note> yea, he shall make all things new; and in that day of his appearing and Kingdome, he shall judge the quick and the dead, for all shall be raised and appeare before his Judgment-seat, every man in his own order; and then shall he reward every man according to his work. This assures us, that his Kingdome, of which his Saints (as Saints) are heirs, is not of this world, nor to be possessed or enjoyed any other way then by faith (which is the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of things not seen, the confidence of things hoped for; we say, not any other way to be enjoyed) by any in the time of this present life in the flesh, or by any till they shall all be gathered together, and himself come to be with them, untill they be the children of the resurrection, and so compleated the children of God. Men (as men) are children and heirs of this world, and of the Kingdomes thereof; believers (as believers) are heirs of the world to come; therefore they are not to fight for Christs Kingdome, of which they are heirs, but to believe, wait, and suffer patiently for it; for this is not the time of the glorious manifestation of it; it's the Fathers good pleasure to give it them in his time, and when they shall be altogether made meet for it, and till then they cannot take &amp; possess it, and that is not till he come himself perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally in the glory of his Father, and then God will give it him whose right it is for himself, and for them. He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves will not make haste, and not making haste shall not be confounded. The time we have to live every one in the flesh, is a suffering time; and till himself come and bring them that sleep in Jesus with him, it's to them all<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>; waiting time; and the excellency and blessedness of that hope, with the certainty of the ground, instructs and strengthens patiently to wait for the coming of the Lord while we look not at the things that are seen, but at the things that are not seen; for the things that are seen are temporall, but the things that are not seen are eternall.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:211280:12"/>
            <head>An Instruction Occasioned By the PRIDE and INSURRECTION of Evil men, Under pretence of GODLINESSE; As it was propounded to the consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of others in writing, <hi>Jan.</hi> 16. 1660. Now published for more general usefulness, By TH: MOORE Junior.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>WOe to the world, because of offences;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 18.7.</note>
               <hi>for it must must needs be that offences come, but woe to that man by whom the offence cometh.</hi> Our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our having declared how sad and dangerous a thing it is to <hi>offend one of those little ones which believe in him;</hi> that so he might warn his Disciples against it whatever occasion might be offered them: He then adds to the same pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose this <hi>woe to the world because of offences,</hi> but espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to <hi>that man by whom the offence cometh:</hi> In which (it seems to me) he speaks of such occasions of offence, or
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:211280:13"/>stumbling-blocks laid before the men of the world, as would have much in them to provoke them to <hi>offend those little ones which believe in him,</hi> or to do things to the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, hinderance and grief of them; and of these he saith, <hi>It must needs be that offences come:</hi> and this he declares to be a woe, a great affliction or misery to the world, a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection or judgement upon them, it being a great means of blinding and hardening them against Christ and his lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ones, and so of bringing destruction on themselves. But therefore woe especially to the man by whom the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence cometh, God will look upon him or them as the principall agents in the grievance and hard measure occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioned to his little ones from the world by such offences, &amp; in the evil and misery the world bring upon themselves by that meanes, and will require their bloud at the hands of such, as by whom the offence cometh. Therefore take we all heed of it, that we give no just occasion of offence in any thing to the Jew or Gentile, or to the Church of God; I say, that we give no just cause or occasion: for then onely we are truly said to give offence, or the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence that others take cometh by us; whereas if they take offence at us, and <hi>persecute us for righteousness sake,</hi> for being <hi>followers of that which is good,</hi> the offence then co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not by us, 'tis the offence of the Cross of Christ; and he will take that as done to himself from them.</p>
            <p>Now we give just occasion of offence, and lay a stum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling-block in their way, to stumble them against Christ his truth and people; if any of us, while we pretend, or seek to be justified by Christ, and to have all our rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing in him, yet are found sinners, allowing and justify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our selves in any evil way or work, contrary to Gods law; or refusing, neglecting, or omitting any good work required of us by the powers set over us, or to the doing which we have opportunity, or <hi>using our liberty</hi> in Christ, as to things indifferent, for a <hi>cloak of</hi> pride or <hi>malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness,</hi> and <hi>not as the servants of God,</hi> as 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13-17.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:211280:13"/>
            <p>And indeed, by whomsoever, or in which of these wayes soever the offence cometh, generally the root is pride, or a will and desire set for great things for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves here, to be rich in themselves, or have a self-suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency, or to be known, honored and exalted above others in this present world, as appears by considering the occasion of these sayings of our Saviour, which we find (in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of that <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.) to be the ambition of some of the Disciples; their desire of eminency in the Kingdome, of chief place, honour, and rule therein, in the time of this present life and world; yea,
<note place="margin">Pro. 13.10. with Jam. 3.13-17. &amp; 4.1-6.</note>
               <hi>onely by pride cometh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention,</hi> and therewith <hi>confusion, and every evil work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence it is that many, especially in these last dayes, that have <hi>a form of godliness</hi> (even of worshipping God in Christ, and seeking his Kingdom) yet not acknowledging the riches, freeness and truth of Gods grace in Christ to manward, and so not the infinite vertue, preciousness and onely excellency of the Cross of Christ, for bringing back sinners to God, and for saving to the utmost him that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth; that being indeed the power of God unto salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; so the power of godliness; they not with the heart believing this, or not so receiving the love of the truth, as to save them, but denying its instructions and efficacy upon them, which is to crucify them to the world, and the world to them, to teach and strengthen them to deny themselves, and take up their cross and follow him, and to wait for his Son from heaven: But their soul being lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted up with their knowledge and attainments, and not humbled in them; they are found in their works denying him, and casting off his yoke, and <hi>seeking great things for themselves</hi> here, and yet that under pretence of godliness and seeking his Kingdom, under which they strengthen themselves in an evil way, as if thereby they were delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from all laws and rules of instruction given us in the Scripture to do any abomination, as to be truce-breakers, railers, speaking evil of Dignities, disobedient to Parents &amp; Governours, unthankfull, unholy, profane, Murtherers, Traitors, <hi>&amp;c,</hi> And by reason of the abounding of such
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:211280:14"/>iniquity, ungodliness and unrighteousness of men, who hold something of the truth (though in unrighteousness) and smother and withhold it all from its humbling and sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving operation in them; the name of God is blasphemed among the Gentiles by their means; the way of truth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil spoken of, and the Ministry that believers have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of the Lord, to testify to the grace of God, blamed, as if Christ (as preached in the Gospel) were the Minister of Sin, or the way of Truth were the way of Falshood, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, guile, murther, revenge, and the Ministry were a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistry and spawn of sedition, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And <hi>wo to the world, because of</hi> such <hi>offences:</hi> And why woe to them, and not rather woe to Christs <hi>little flock,</hi> his despised ones, that <hi>keep the word of his patience,</hi> or his <hi>little ones</hi> in any sence, that are by his gracious imputation and acceptation believers in him? seeing they are like to suffer the deepest share of the influence of such offences here; for the world cannot distinguish between the form and power of godliness, nor know them that call on the name of the Lord <hi>in truth,</hi> and with a <hi>pure heart,</hi> from them who <hi>having a form of godliness deny the power;</hi> they will look upon them all under one notion, and be filled with indignation and hatred against them all, and seek to grieve, vex and destroy all that have any profession of godliness, even the righteous with the wicked: Why then doth he not rather say, Woe to the Church, yea to all that have any profession or form of godliness upon them? for because of such offences they shall be straitned, persecuted and reproached as evil doers, and have their names cast out as evil under heaven. True it is, they shall so, and especially <hi>they that will live godly in Christ Jesus,</hi> shall <hi>mourn</hi> under manifold afflictions (though such as having a form deny the power of godliness may sometimes rage and be confident, and otherwhiles be mad and blaspheme) and the <hi>world shall rejoyce:</hi> But yet rather woe to the world, then to the little ones of Christ; though their <hi>righteous soules be vexed and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi> on every hand, yet there is no such cause of weeping
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:211280:14"/>for them, as for the world, that yet lies in ignorance, and under the power of the wicked one, because of the mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries that shall come upon them; for they hereby are kept from glorifying God in the day of his visitation, and strengthened in their evil principles and practises, that none of them returnes from them, and hardened against these little ones; yea happily the more against them, as any of them are known to them, rather then against others that have a form of godliness, but deny the power, because their doctrine rightly held forth and walked in, is more convincing and reproving to them; and yet they know not how to resist the wisdom and spirit by which they speak and act, but not discerning between the one and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and now finding these occasions and advantages a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst some that bear such a like profession, they streng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then and harden their hearts against all, and against Christ and his truth; the power of which they have sometimes felt amongst or from his little ones; and then without controul or check upon their spirits, they proceed in their hardness, to seek the restraining of their liberty, vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, persecuting and slaying them; and this tends to bring heavy wrath on themselves, that will render them miserable to the utmost: For <hi>vengeance belongs to God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 32.35, 36.</note> and though he be <hi>slow to anger,</hi> and wait long that he may be gracious, yet he will repay to <hi>such as go on still in their trespasses;</hi> and again, <hi>the Lord shall judge his people;</hi> therefore <hi>woe to the world because of offences.</hi> As for them that <hi>keep the word of his patience, they shall be kept from the hour of temptation,</hi> from the evil of it; and for all their shame they shall have double glory, and in their own hand possess it. But <hi>woe to the world,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>for it must needs be that offences come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That they that are approved may be manifest,</hi> as also that they may be tried and purged, and made more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly partakers of his holiness, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.19. <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.10. &amp; 11.35. <hi>Isa.</hi> 48.10.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That others also more weak, wavering, or guilefull, may be discovered to themselves and others, and that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:211280:15"/>timely, while it's yet to day, that they may be reproved and healed, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.32. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.10.</p>
            <p n="3">3.
<note place="margin">Rom. 1.18, 32. with Psal. 18.11, 12. &amp; 2 Thes. 2.10, 11. Prov. 1.31, 32.</note> That for the good of all, while it is to day, or while the day of grace is towards them, God may righteously reveal his wrath from heaven (not onely against some, but) against all ungodliness and unrighteousness of men, who hold the truth in unrighteousness, perverting and corrupting the word God to their own destruction, in his just leaving them to reap the fruit of their own wayes, and to be filled with their own devices, and sending strong delusions to them, that they should believe a lye, or giving them up to their own hearts lusts, and to the power of the tempter; and that he may do this seasonably, for the warning the survivers to <hi>flee from the wrath to come,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. His wrath (in such judgements) is revealed against the ungodliness and unrighteousness of such men, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving had some knowledge of the way of truth more then others, and still retaining a form of godliness, and happily more flourishning in appearance,
<note place="margin">2 Thes. 2.10, 11. Rom. 2.17-24. 2 Pet. 2.2.</note> yet deny the power of it (as before) and whose soul is lifted up, not so receiving the love of the truth, as to humble and to save them; his wrath is revealed against such, in giving them up to their own delusions that they have chosen suitable to their lust, and to be led captive by Satan at his pleasure, to the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioning offences to the world, and so blasphemy to the name and doctrine of God, and way of truth, and grief to the righteous from them; which will all fall on their head, if not timely admonished, even to their own confusion and destruction.</p>
            <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">Psal. 11.6.</note> Wrath is therein revealed against the ungodliness and unrighteousness of another sort, more grosly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, superstitious and idolatrous, in ordering such stum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling-blocks to them, that they may be broken, snared and taken; in leaving them to their own hearts lusts, and to their ungodliness and unrighteousness, without such humblings and reproofs as formerly, even to fill up the measure of their sin, that wrath may come upon them to the uttermost, if not timely prevented by their being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked to jealousie.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:211280:15"/>
            <p n="3">3. Wrath is revealed against all hearers, that are not doers of the word of the Lord, by his taking away in the influence of such judgements, the mercies, liberties and advantages they have made havock of; and this is good and needful to be timely revealed, for the warning all, while it is to day, that those not wholly given over to blindness may see and fear: And for such reasons it must needs be that offences come, and therefore wo to the world: but woe, woe especially to the man, or men by whom they come; it may be easier to them, that being offended by such temptations and offences, do from thence offend and grieve Christs little ones; I say, <hi>easier for them in the day of judgement, then for him,</hi> or them by whom the offence cometh.</p>
            <p>Therefore though we know these things, and be establi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed in the present truth of the Kingdom and patience of Jesus; yet let us have them alwayes in remembrance, that so by the word of his lips we may keep us from the paths of the destroyer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is the Fathers good pleasure</hi> (who hath given his one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly begotten Son to suffer even to death for us all,
<note place="margin">Luke 12.32.</note> when sinners and enemies) to give unto those little ones, who though his grace in Christ to manward believe on him, the everlasting life &amp; <hi>kingdom;</hi> but it is <hi>not of this world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 18.36</note> nor in the time of this present world to be possessed, but by faith and hope, which is the <hi>evidence of things not seen,</hi> or sensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly enjoyed, the <hi>confidence of things hoped for;</hi> God hath reserved <hi>the new heavens and earth, the world to come,</hi> for those that now suffer with him, and patiently wait for the Lord, and they shall inherit it, and then shall judge the world, as reigners with him. But now, though both the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens and earth are the Lords, both by creation and redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption also, yet the earth is not so kept by him in his own hand, or not so under his own immediate government by Jesus Christ, and by his holy Angels, as the heavens are: Therefore he saith, <hi>The heavens,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ps. 115.16.</note>
               <hi>even the heavens are the Lords, but the earth hath he given to the children of men;</hi> the <hi>Kingdomes of this world</hi> are not yet, nor shall in the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:211280:16"/>time of this world, so <hi>become the kingdomes of the Lord, and of his Christ,</hi> that he should <hi>take to him his great power and reign;</hi> for that is spoken of as seen in vision, to be fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led under the sound of the seventh Angel, when there should be <hi>time no longer</hi> afforded to this present world;
<note place="margin">Rev. 11.15-17. &amp; 10.6, 7. Luk. 20.34</note> but <hi>the mysterie of God should be finished, as he hath declared to his servants the Prophets;</hi> in the mean time, men (as men) are the proper children and heirs of this world, and the kingdoms and heritages thereof; and so if the Saints of God have any share in the kingdoms or heritages of this world, they have not their right and title to the same as Saints (so they are heirs of the world to come) but as men, upon a humane, naturall, or civil account; and those that are not Saints, as upon such accounts, they have right to any thing in this earth, their right and title is as good (as to the present possession of it) as if they were Saints or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers in Christ:
<note place="margin">Psa. 17.14.</note> the men of the world have their portion in this life, and it's fraud or robbery to seek to withhold or take it from them. And therefore believing servants (even such as are under the yoke of unbelieving Masters) are instructed to <hi>count their own masters</hi> in or <hi>after the flesh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.1. with 1 Pet. 2.13-17. &amp; Tit. 2.9, 10. with ch. 3.1</note>
               <hi>worthy of all honour,</hi> even of all that honour God by his providence hath given them, and made due to them, by putting them in that place of mastership. And by not observing this counsel, there is occasion given for the name and doctrine of God in Christ to be blasphemed, as tending to sedition, and lifting men up out of their place in which God hath set them.</p>
            <p>And the same instruction holds good to believers, that by Gods providence are subjects, to count their Kings, Governours, or Rulers after the flesh, worthy of all that honour due to them, as in the place in which God hath set them over us. Therefore <hi>every soul</hi> (even of believers) is admonished to <hi>be subject to the higher powers,</hi> such as by Gods providence are in present being over them, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out disputing how (whether legally or no, as to man) they came by that place (that question pertains not to Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, in order to their submission to the powers over them)
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:211280:16"/>yea this we know, God exercises a more especiall and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate providence in the ordering those places of the higher powers among men;
<note place="margin">Psal. 75. &amp; 82.</note> the power of pulling down and setting up principalities, is more peculiarly reserved by him in his own hand, to be done as he pleaseth, and not left so much unto the power or dispose of men as the outward administration of government over men, which he hath put into their hands, and left more under their power; nor doth God use his Saints (as Saints) as instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of pulling down or setting up, it pertains not to them as such, but God doth it either by his more immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate providences, and those either more ordinary, as in the determining times, life and death in his ordinary way, or more wonderfull and extraordinary, or sometimes by men, as men, sometime by evil instruments, he pulls down and sets up at his pleasure, whether for mercy or chastise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and alwayes wills us to be subject to them, that by his wise and gracious providence are set over us; and that not onely for wrath, but for conscience sake, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for fear of their wrath (or so, and in such cases and times onely, as when we cannot avoyd it, but are awed to it by the wrath of men) but at all times, even for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science sake towards God, who hath set them in such pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces over us, and without whom they could not have had that power, nor can stand in it one day; whatever be their right and will, and whatever their policy and strength to pursue or maintain it: yea, he hath declared it great wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedness to lift up a hand against him that is in the present time, by Gods providence, King, Governour, or Ruler o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us, yea, though he were or should be such as he there mentioned (1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.3 6-10-13.) whom God <hi>gave them in his anger,</hi> Hos. 13.11. or such as those Emperours in <hi>Pauls</hi> time: Neither are the Tares to be pluckt up from among the Wheat, nor the wicked to be severed from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the just, in the present state of the kingdom of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, as in this world administred;
<note place="margin">Mat. 13.40, 41-49, 50.</note> nor are men (as men) capable of doing that work: But in the end of this world, <hi>when the Son of man shall appear from heaven with his migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:211280:17"/>Angels,</hi> and when the children of the first resurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on shall be raised and made equall to the Angels, he shall at that time <hi>send his Angels</hi> to do that work; And <hi>they shall gather out of his kingdome all things that offend, and them that do iniquity;</hi> till then, he bids his servants let them alone, the tares in Christs field, the wicked in his kingdome, as here administred. Nor will Jesus Christ own any (though they pretend commission from him) that go about to pluck them out, or to take the kingdoms of this world out of the hands of the men of the world, to take it to themselves as their portion, or inheritance as Saints, before <hi>the Lord</hi> himself <hi>come,</hi> and <hi>bring all that sleep in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus with him;</hi> for he hath commanded them the contrary, and admonished them, that <hi>his kingdome is not of this world, if it were, his servants might fight</hi> for it; but because it is not, they ought not. This is the time of their suffering with Christ in their several ages, that so they may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to his Image in sufferings now, and through them in the issue of them in glory. <hi>If we suffer with him</hi> in this world (where he suffered all the days of his flesh, and for his names sake, and where that suffers reproach and bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sphemy, and quietly bear and endure it, without retorting and threatning, being followers of his steps, <hi>we shall reign with him, and be glorified together.</hi> But of this be we admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished, there is a great difference between suffering with him, and suffering as evil doers, I mean justly as such; for a man may suffer as a deceiver and traitor, or the like, and suffer wrongfully, he being true. The Apostles were accused of treachery and sedition, sometimes against their own nation, sometimes against the Romans, but wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully; but if a man give just occasion of his sufferings, as such, he hath cause to be ashamed, and not glory in those his sufferings (though yet in taking shame, he may find mercy with him, when there is none with men.)</p>
            <p>Likewise there is great difference between those suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, in which a man takes up his Cross patiently, bearing tryals when they come, enduring them patiently without resisting the evil, whether he meets with them in Gods
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:211280:17"/>way, or they be ordered to him by way of correction to turn him into it; and those sufferings which a man brings on himself by resisting, and seeking to keep them off: let no man glory of such sufferings, as if they were any thing of the Cross of Christ or afflictions of the Gospel, or for his sake, when it's evident, they would have resisted and avoided them, if they could; and meerly procured them, by seeking to save their lives, and avoid the Cross, (yea, that also often in their pride, and self-will) contrary to all Rules of instruction given them by the great Lord and Master, who <hi>came not to be ministred unto, but to minister, and to give his life a ransome for many;</hi> and when he could have prayed for <hi>more then twelve legions of angels,</hi> and had them sent forth to rescue him, would not, but accepted the Cup, though bitter, which the Father gave him to drink: He patiently <hi>endured for the joy set before him</hi> in the glory thereby to be possessed in the same body in which he suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, and for us, <hi>that</hi> so <hi>he might bring us to God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That therefore we may be <hi>armed with the same mind that was in Christ Jesus,</hi> even with a fixed Spirit, singly set for the doing the will of God, and living to that, that his great Name in Christ may be known, and glorified by us, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers may be profited; and so for the quiet bearing and enduring the tryals we may meet with in his way, without resisting or threatning, or being moved from the Faith and Hope in Christ, or from the profession of it, let us first always diligently consider him, as <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.1, 2, 3. 1. Christ himself hath suffered for us in the flesh, even all the days of his flesh; He was a sufferer in his birth, bringing up, life and death, though he was Lord of all, and our Anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted King and Saviour, the Captain of our salvation; yea, <hi>he was made perfect through sufferings:</hi> and surely this was, that his followers should not live this life they have to live, in the flesh, (or natural body) to the lusts of men, (their own or others) but to the will of God; and so al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, that they should <hi>live this life in the flesh,</hi> (not by a sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible enjoyment of the hope of his calling, but) <hi>by Faith in the Son of God, who loved us, and gave himself for us.</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:211280:18"/>And if such things happened to the Lord and Master of the houshold all his life-time here in the flesh, (in this state of mortality in which yet we are) why should any of the houshold count it hard measure to have such use in the world, and such sufferings in the flesh as he graciously or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to us, that we may be conformed to his image? If he patiently endured who might have resisted, why should any of us murmur, or not take it patiently, <hi>for as much as Christ also suffered in the flesh, leaving us an example that we should follow his steps?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, 2. He suffered all those unspeakable great things that were laid on him by the Father, and from the hands of men, for us, even for us that were sinners, altogether filthy,
<note place="margin">☞</note> and enemies to him, and yet cryed not against us that occasioned those sufferings to him. VVhereas what he calls us to suffer, is for him that hath so loved us, as to lay down his life for us when we were enemies; and is the God, and Fountain of our lives, and of all our mercies, and that by means of his death. Yea, he suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for our sins, whereas our sufferings are for his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness sake, if we suffer with him; or however, they are by his righteous order, and so in and by the hands of a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator, for the purging away our sin, and making us parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of his holiness, who would not willingly and chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully follow his steps.</p>
            <p>Seeing also, 3. Through his sufferings the way is made possible, that we may follow him, and receive no harm thereby, but much good by the savour of his oyntments left behind him; for he <hi>having born our sins in his own body on the tree,</hi> hath not left them for us to feel the weight of them in the wrath due for them in our sufferings, but hath nailed them to the tree; being raised from the dead, he hath by himself purged away our sins from before God, and obtained all power to forgive all our sins, and heal all our diseases, and himself (having redeemed us from the curse of the law, and obtained plenteous and eternall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption for us, that the blessing of <hi>Abraham</hi> might come upon us) is become in the Name of the Father, the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:211280:18"/>great Apostle and high Priest of our profession, and the head over all things to the Church. So that we are not in any of our sufferings left under the power or will of any adversary, but by him the kingdom of God is brought to us, and rules over us; none can do any thing beyond his permission, and he will watch over us for good, and be a present help in time of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; seeing also, <hi>Though our iniquities testifie against us,</hi> yet <hi>with him there is forgivenesse, that he may be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> and hoped in by us: and in due time he will fully deliver &amp; <hi>redeem Israel from all his troubles. He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves will not make haste;</hi> and not making haste, he shall not be confounded. And with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> consideration &amp; retaining in the heart this hope, with the reason of it (as given us in Christ Jesus) which we shall find powerfull to teach, strengthen &amp; save us; let us also be willing in the day of his power, as he is (by the preaching of the Cross of Christ, and by his judgements) working us to will and to do, mortify, cut off, and cast from us such desires, affections and purposes, set upon things here below, as are discovered and reproved by his grace bringing salvation; they otherwise will prove treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to us, and occasion us to fall in a day of tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: As to say, the love to the praise of men,
<note place="margin">Joh. 5.44. &amp; 12.42. &amp;c. Jam. 4.3, 4.</note> or to be known and owned as sons of God in the world; a will to be rich, or the love of money, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.9, 10. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.32, 33. <hi>Psal.</hi> 119.36, 37. as in any measure we have found Christ, so <hi>for the excellency of the knowledge of him, all things are to be</hi> parted with <hi>as losse</hi> and <hi>dung,</hi> else we cannot go on to know and <hi>win him,</hi> and <hi>be found in him.</hi> See the many admonitions to this purpose, not onely in the following part of that <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. <hi>Mark</hi> 9. &amp;c. But also in <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.24. &amp;c. <hi>John</hi> 12.25. &amp;c. <hi>Luke</hi> 14.26-33. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.44-46.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:211280:19"/>
            <p>Consider what is said, and the Lord of his mercy make us wise and strong in the grace that is in Christ Jesus, that we be not moved by any afflictions (though we suffer wrongfully) either from <hi>holding fast the profession of our faith,</hi> or to do any evil, in murmuring against, or <hi>spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king evil of dignities,</hi> or <hi>striving,</hi> or <hi>threatning</hi> when we suffer, but <hi>commit our selves to him that judgeth righteously:</hi> yea, let Gods mercy be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred and acknowledged, which he hath shewed towards us in all the administration of his government over us in manifold changes, and especially beyond what could have bin expected (considering the offences that have come by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny professing godlinesse) under this our King and present government; for whom, and for which let us pray, that under the same Gods peculiar people may yet have opportunity to <hi>lead a quiet and peaceable life in all godlinesse and honesty.</hi> And if by occasion of offences given by others we suffer, <hi>take it patiently; in so doing, the spirit of Glory and of God shall rest upon us:</hi> threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten not, but <hi>pray for them that persecute us;</hi> nor do any thing <hi>through strife or vain-glory,</hi> but <hi>walk in wisdome towards them that are without,</hi> even in the wisdome of God, and in that (and not as self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will or pride might move us) <hi>redeem the time,</hi> &amp; improve the opportunities God may afford, in endeavouring the helpfulness of our selves, and one another in the faith and patience of Jesus, looking for the mercy of God unto eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, and meddle not with things that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:211280:19"/>not to us, <hi>nor have fellowship with</hi> any in their <hi>unfruitfull works of darkness, but rather reprove <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem:</hi> And the Lord so direct us all, and sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e us wholly, and preserve us blameless unto the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y of Christ.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>
            <hi>FINIS.</hi>
            <pb facs="tcp:211280:20"/>
         </trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>